Guide to the Lee Wulff Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lee Wulff papers
1914-2005
1960-1991
GEN MSS 946
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
18.26
(20 boxes) + 1 art
The Lee Wulff Papers contain drafts, setting copies, and proofs of books, and drafts of magazine articles and reports by Wulff, with related correspondence and reviews; correspondence and related printed material; biographical clippings and obituaries; photographs of Wulff and his family, and photographs of early paintings by him; and flies and fly lines made by Wulff or designed by him. Research strengths include Wulff's writings on fishing, hunting, and conservation; catch and release fishing; fly fishing techniques, equipment, education, and the Wulff School of Fly Fishing; Wulff's design and marketing of fly fishing equipment, and Royal Wulff Products; hunting and fishing in Newfoundland and Labrador; conservation of the Atlantic salmon; and hunting, fishing, and conservation organizations in the United States and Canada, 1930s-1990s.
Wulff, Lee, 1905-1991
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Joan Wulff on the Jonathan O. Bulkley Fund, 2005; and gift of Joan Wulff, 2008-2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 21 (objects): Restricted fragile material. Reference images may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Lee Wulff (1905-1991)
Fly fisher, author, conservationist, artist, and filmmaker. Wulff invented fly fishing techniques and equipment, advocated catch and release fishing and Atlantic salmon conservation, and popularized fishing and hunting through his writings and films. He married Joan Salvato Wulff (1926-), fly fisher and author, with whom he founded the Wulff School of Fly Fishing, on the Beaverkill River, New York, in 1979, and Royal Wulff Products, a fly fishing equipment business.
Scope and Contents
The Lee Wulff Papers contain drafts, setting copies, and proofs of books, and drafts of magazine articles and reports by Wulff, with related correspondence and reviews; correspondence and related printed material; biographical clippings and obituaries; photographs of Wulff and his family, and photographs of early paintings by him; and flies and fly lines made by Wulff or designed by him. Research strengths include Wulff's writings on fishing, hunting, and conservation; catch and release fishing; fly fishing techniques, equipment, education, and the Wulff School of Fly Fishing; Wulff's design and marketing of fly fishing equipment, and Royal Wulff Products; hunting and fishing in Newfoundland and Labrador; conservation of the Atlantic salmon; and hunting, fishing, and conservation organizations in the United States and Canada, 1930s-1990s.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Writings, 1938-1999. II. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1930s-2005. III. Photographs, 1914-1988. IV. Objects, undated.
Atlantic salmon -- Conservation; Atlantic salmon fishing -- United States; Conservation of natural resources -- United States; Fishers -- United States; Flies, Artificial -- United States; Fly fishing -- Equipment and supplies; Fly fishing -- Canada; Fly fishing -- United States; Fly fishing for women -- United States; Hunting -- United States; Women fishers -- United States; Audiovisual materials -- United States -- 20th Century; DVDs -- United States -- 21st century; Fishing tackle -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 21st century; Fishers -- United States -- 20th Century; Wulff, Joan Salvato; Wulff, Lee, 1905-1991; Atlantic Salmon Association; Atlantic Salmon Federation; Royal Wulff Products; Wulff School of Fly Fishing
- Writings, 1938-1999; Series I; 6.25; (7 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Books, Magazine Articles, and Other Writings. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by title, followed by unsorted materials.
  Scope and Contents
  Writings concern fly fishing, hunting, and conservation, some with related correspondence, photographs, or research materials.
  - Books
    - The Atlantic Salmon
      - Correspondence, undated; 4 (Box 1)
      - Galley proofs, 1981-1982; 4 (Box 1)
      - Photographs, 1983 revision, 6 (Box 1)
    - Bush Pilot Angler
      Memoir
      Working title: Yellowbird
      - Correspondence, 1985-1999 (Box 1)
      - Draft, computer printout with manuscript revisions, "corrected MS", 1990; 8 (Box 1)
      - Draft, computer printout, "no notes", undated; 2 (Box 1)
      - Drafts, mostly typescript carbon and computer printout; notes; and research materials, undated; 2 (Box 1)
      - Drafts, mostly typescript carbon and computer printout; notes; and research materials, undated; 6 (Box 2)
      - Draft, typescript carbon and typescript photocopy, with manuscript revisions, "Old MS", undated; 3 (Box 2)
      - Draft, typescript photocopy, with manuscript notes by Allan Wulff, 1987; 2 (Box 2)
      - Draft, typescript photocopy, with manuscript notes by John McDonald, 1985; 3 (Box 2)
      - Draft, typescript photocopy, with manuscript revisions and notes by Nick Lyon, 1986; 2 (Box 2)
      - Draft, typescript photocopy, with manuscript revisions and notes by Nick Lyon, "Yellowbird and Salmon", undated; 3 (Box 2)
      - Draft, typescript with manuscript revisions, photocopy, 1991 March; 3 (Box 3)
    - The Complete Lee Wulff: A Treasury of Lee Wulff's Greatest Angling Adventures
      Essay collection
      Working title: The Essential Lee Wulff
      - Draft, computer printout, "Lee's copy", 1988 Nov 3; 2 (Box 3)
      - Draft, computer printout, with manuscript revisions, "revised copy", 1988 Nov 17; 4 (Box 3)
      - Reviews, 1989, undated (Box 3)
    - Fishing with Lee Wulff
      - Correspondence and drafts, undated (Box 3)
    - Leaping Silver
      - Advertisments, photograph, and review, 1940 (Box 3)
    - Lee Wulff on Flies
      - Draft, typescript carbon, and page proof, undated; 3 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1973-1984 (Box 3)
      - Galley proofs, corrected, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Lee Wulff's New Handbook of Freshwater Fishing
      - Drafts, typescript, with manuscript revisions, 1939; 3 (Box 3)
      - Reviews and royalty statements, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Let's Go Fishing: A Boy's Book on Freshwater Fishing
      - Draft, computer printout with manuscript revisions, and correspondence, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Salmon on a Fly: The Essential Wisdom and Lore from a Lifetime of Salmon Fishing
      - Draft, typescript, undated (Box 3)
      - Draft, typescript, undated; 2 (Box 4)
      - Setting copy, with printer's annotations, undated; 3 (Box 4)
      - Page proof, fragment (Box 4)
    - Sports Photography
      - Reviews, 1942 (Box 4)
    - The Sportsman's Companion
      - Reviews, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Trout on a Fly
      - Draft, "I," computer printout with manuscript revisions, undated; 4 (Box 4)
      - Reviews, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
      - Illustrations, drafts, undated (Box 4)
  - Magazine Articles
    Most magazine articles are typescript or typescript photocopy, with manuscript revisions
    - Titles, A-P, undated; 11 (Box 4)
    - Titles, Q-Y, undated; 8 (Box 5)
    - Atlantic Salmon Journal, undated; 2 (Box 5)
    - Miller Brewing Company, undated; 2 (Box 5)
    - Rod & Reel, "Wulff's Run", undated; 2 (Box 5)
    - Other magazine articles. Notes and drafts, undated; 6 (Box 5)
    - Other magazine articles, "Not on any list." Clippings., undated (Box 5)
    - Lists of articles, undated (Box 5)
    - Unsorted, 1938-1991, undated; 9 (Box 5)
    - Unsorted, 1938-1991, undated; 8 (Box 6)
    - Unsorted, 1938-1964; 6 (Box 20 (Oversize))
  - Other Writings
    - Book contracts, 1938-1944 (Box 6)
    - "Bourke Journal." Typescript photocopy, with photocopies of related documents and photographs, undated; 2 (Box 6)
      Transcript of a journal by Joseph A. Bourke about a trip from Brooklyn to Alaska during the 1898 gold rush, with Bill Wagner and Charlie Wulff, Lee Wulff's father
    - Early writings, 1915-1924 (Box 6)
    - "Man and the Animals." Drafts, typescript and typescript carbon; notes; correspondence; and research materials, undated; 8 (Box 6)
    - Reports for Canadian government: "Newfoundland Government Business", undated; 3 (Box 6)
    - Reports for Canadian government, undated; 7 (Box 6)
    - "Rivers in My Mind." Notes and drafts, undated (Box 6)
      Collection of essays about rivers
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 6)
- Correspondence and Subject Files, 1930s-2005; Series II; 11.42; (12 boxes)
  Related Archival Materials note
  Additional correspondence is in Series I, Writings.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Files contain mostly correspondence; also present are notes, clippings, and other printed material. Correspondents include publishers, fly fishing equipment businesses, fishing and conservation organizations, friends, colleagues, and fans. Some files contain biographical information, family correspondence, or other family papers.
  - "Air Force", undated (Box 7)
  - "Angling Feats"
    - General, undated; 2 (Box 7)
    - "Jock Scott", undated; 2 (Box 7)
    - "Steelhead #28 Controversy", undated (Box 7)
  - "Appearances"
    - General, 1957-1990; 12 (Box 7)
    - "Executive Club of Chicago", 1947-1973; 2 (Box 7)
  - "Atlantic Salmon", 1960s-1976; 12 (Box 7)
  - "Atlantic Salmon", 1976-1991; 24 (Box 8)
  - Atlantic Salmon Federation
    - Conservation Board, undated (Box 9)
    - Code of Ethics, undated (Box 9)
    - Programs, 1981-1991; 2 (Box 9)
  - "Aviation"
    - General, undated; 2 (Box 9)
    - "Personal Airports", undated; 3 (Box 9)
  - "Biography", undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - Biographical Information
    - Clippings and other printed material, undated; 4 (Box 9)
    - Magazine articles about Lee Wulff, 1939-2002; 23 (Box 9)
    - Magazine articles about Lee Wulff, 1939-2002; 10 (Box 10)
    - Medical records, 1980 December (Box 10)
    - Obituaries, undated; 3 (Box 10)
  - "Business Affiliations"
    - General, undated; 2 (Box 10)
    - "Norm Thompson", undated; 2 (Box 10)
    - "Orvis Company", undated; 4 (Box 10)
  - "Camps - Newfoundland", undated (Box 10)
  - "Catch and Release", undated (Box 10)
  - "Clubs and Organizations"
    - "Anglers Club of N.Y.", undated; 3 (Box 10)
    - "Salt Water Fly Rodders of America", undated; 2 (Box 10)
    - A-C, undated; 2 (Box 10)
    - D-R, undated; 2 (Box 10)
    - S-Z, undated; 2 (Box 10)
  - "International Game Fish Association" (IGFA), undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - "Conservation - Miscellaneous", undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - "Conservation Activities"
    - "Sport Fishing Institute", undated (Box 11)
    - "Trout Unlimited", undated; 4 (Box 11)
    - "Federation of Fly Fisherman" (FFF)
      - Correspondence, 1964-1967; 3 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence, 1968-1975; 3 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1982; 3 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence, 1983-1991; 3 (Box 11)
      - Publications, undated; 2 (Box 11)
    - "Trout Unlimited"
      - "Trout Magazine", undated (Box 11)
      - "Lee Wulff chapter", undated (Box 11)
    - "Tuna"
      - General, undated; 3 (Box 12)
      - "Articles", undated (Box 12)
      - "New Brunswick", undated (Box 12)
      - "Nova Scotia", undated (Box 12)
      - "Prince Edward Island", undated (Box 12)
    - "U.S. Fish and Wildlife Services", undated (Box 12)
  - "Contributions to Other Writers' Projects", undated; 4 (Box 12)
  - "Family", undated (Box 12)
  - "Fans and Admirers", 1960-1969; 4 (Box 12)
  - "Fans and Admirers", 1970-1980; 3 (Box 12)
  - "Fans and Admirers", 1981-1991; 4 (Box 12)
  - Film Production
    - "ABC - American Sportsman", undated; 3 (Box 12)
    - "ABC - Norway", 1967 (Box 12)
    - "Audio Tapes", undated (Box 12)
    - "Business", undated; 3 (Box 13)
    - "Business - music releases", undated (Box 13)
    - "Capital Airlines", undated (Box 13)
    - "CBS Sports Spectacular", undated; 2 (Box 13)
    - "CBS - NYT Clippings - Africa Trip", undated (Box 13)
    - "Committee on the Atlantic Salmon Emergency", undated; 3 (Box 13)
    - "Doug Sinclair", undated (Box 13)
    - "Equipment", undated (Box 13)
    - "Film Contests and Awards", undated; 2 (Box 13)
    - "Film Proposals", undated (Box 13)
    - "Garcia", 1959-1975; 4 (Box 13)
    - "Lab", undated (Box 13)
    - "Miller Bass Film", undated (Box 13)
    - "Newfoundland", undated (Box 13)
    - "Newfoundland Enterprise", 1944 (Box 13)
    - "Newfoundland Government Film", 1957-1976; 6 (Box 13)
    - "Newfoundland Newspaper Clippings", 1938 (Box 13)
    - "North American Outdoorsman", undated (Box 13)
    - "Nova Scotia", undated (Box 13)
    - "Old Crow - National Distillers", undated; 2 (Box 14)
    - "Phillip Morris - Miller Brewing", undated (Box 14)
    - "Queries to Potential Sponsors", undated; 3 (Box 14)
    - "Sport Series Ideas", undated; 2 (Box 14)
    - "Still Photography", undated (Box 14)
    - "Videocassettes - L.W. Outdoor Classics", undated (Box 14)
    - Winchester Western: "Winchester", undated; 2 (Box 14)
    - Lee Wulff Master Collection (Royal Wulff Products), c2005 (Box 14)
      Conditions Governing Access
      DVDs: use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      14 films, originally 16mm, on 2 DVDs
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 14)
  - "Fish and Game Law", undated (Box 14)
  - "Fishing Equipment Designed by Lee Wulff", 1982, undated (Box 14)
  - "Fly Fishing Museums", undated (Box 14)
  - "Friends"
    - Unsorted, undated (Box 14)
    - "A", undated; 3 (Box 14)
    - "B", undated; 4 (Box 14)
    - Butcher, Okey, undated (Box 14)
    - "C", undated; 3 (Box 14)
    - "Colby, Lester", 1964-1988; 2 (Box 14)
    - "Cullman, Joseph", 1961-1990; 2 (Box 14)
    - "D-E", undated; 2 (Box 15)
    - "F-G", undated; 3 (Box 15)
    - "Grant, Gardner", 1977-1990 (Box 15)
    - "Groth, John. Art and correspondence", undated (Box 15)
    - "H-I", undated; 2 (Box 15)
    - "J", undated; 2 (Box 15)
    - "K-L", undated; 3 (Box 15)
    - "M", undated; 3 (Box 15)
    - "Marvin, Neil", 1949-1990; 2 (Box 15)
    - "N-P", undated; 3 (Box 15)
    - "Q-R", undated; 4 (Box 15)
    - "S-V", undated; 4 (Box 15)
    - "Solo, Rob", undated (Box 16)
    - "W-Z", undated; 4 (Box 16)
    - "White, Tommy", undated; 2 (Box 16)
  - "The Garcia Corporation", 1968-1975; 6 (Box 16)
  - "Godfrey, Joe - Fishing Hall of Fame", undated (Box 16)
  - "Iceland", undated (Box 16)
  - "Innovations"
    - "Flies: General, Plastic Bodies", 1960-1971; 3 (Box 16)
    - "Flies: General, Plastic Bodies", 1972-1990; 3 (Box 16)
    - "Fly Lines, Reels, Rods, Lee's Turtle Trap (as a child)", undated; 3 (Box 16)
    - "Salmon Tailor, Vest, and Miscellaneous", undated; 2 (Box 16)
  - "Joan and Lee Wulff, Inc. (1984 Catalog)" (Box 16)
  - "Minipi, Labrador" (Canada), undated (Box 16)
  - "New Hampshire Fish & Game Commission", undated; 6 (Box 16)
  - "Periodicals," A-F, undated; 4 (Box 17)
  - "Periodicals," G-Q, undated; 2 (Box 17)
  - "Periodicals," R, undated (Box 17)
  - "Periodicals," S-Z, undated; 4 (Box 17)
  - "Publicity", 1930s (Box 17)
  - "Publicity", 1940s (Box 17)
  - "Publicity", 1950s (Box 17)
  - "Publicity", 1960-1966; 2 (Box 17)
  - "Publicity", 1967 (Box 17)
  - "Publicity", 1968 (Box 17)
  - "Radio"
    - General, undated (Box 17)
    - "Fishing Broadcasts - Newfoundland", undated (Box 17)
  - "Sandhill River Salmon Club Ltd.", undated; 2 (Box 17)
  - "South Africa", undated (Box 17)
  - "Speeches", undated (Box 17)
  - "Tackle"
    - General, undated (Box 17)
    - "Thomas and Thomas", undated (Box 17)
  - "Tournaments: Palm Beach Masters", 1970 (Box 17)
  - "Writers," A-C, undated; 3 (Box 17)
  - "Writers," D-K, undated; 3 (Box 17)
  - "Writers," L-M, undated; 2 (Box 17)
  - "Writers," N-R, undated; 3 (Box 17)
  - "Writers," S-Z, undated; 4 (Box 18)
  - "Writing Associations", undated; 3 (Box 18)
  - "Writing - Books Correspondence", undated (Box 18)
  - "Youth", undated (Box 18)
  - Bow hunting license, 1953 (Box 18)
  - Empty original folders, undated (Box 18)
  - Certificate of Membership in the New England Regional Fishery Management Council, 1976 (Box 20 (Oversize))
- Photographs, 1914-1988; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  Additional photographs are in Series I, Writings.
  - Photographs of Lee Wulff, Joan Wulff, and other family, 1914-1988, undated (Box 19)
  - Photographs of paintings by Lee Wulff, undated (Box 19)
  - Photographs of paintings by others, 1981, undated (Box 19)
- Objects, undated; Series IV; 0.38; (1 box)
  - Garcia fly line, undated (Box 19)
    With container and instructions
  - Royal Wulff Products fly line, undated (Box 19)
    Container and instructions only
  - Flies made by Lee Wulff, undated; 22 flies, some with identification tags or notes (Box 21 (Art))
    Restricted fragile material. Reference images may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.